<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl"
        type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ident="ab" module="linking" mode="change">
  <gloss xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-06-30">anonymer Textblock</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-30">anonymous block</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-06-30">bloc anonyme</gloss>
  <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-02-05">Enthält einen beliebigen Textblock ohne klar
      definierte Zuordnung.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2025-02-05">Contains any text block without a clearly defined
      assignment.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-02-05">Contient un bloc de texte quelconque sans
      affectation clairement définie.</desc>
  <classes mode="replace">
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.global.rendition"/>
    <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.written"/>
    <memberOf key="macro.abContent"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <sequence maxOccurs="unbounded">
      <macroRef key="ssrq.content.default"/>
    </sequence>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec xml:lang="en" scheme="schematron" ident="sch-el-ab">
    <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2025-05-08">constraints for tei:ab</desc>
    <constraint>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ab[tei:hi]">
          <sch:report test=".[count(*) = 1][string-length(normalize-space(string-join(text(), ''))) = 0]" xml:lang="en" role="warning">
            If no further text is used inside <sch:name/> and tei:hi is the only child, consider
            using the rend-attribute of <sch:name/>.
          </sch:report>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ab[@type='marginal_note']">
          <sch:assert test=".[@place[contains(., 'margin')]]" xml:lang="en">
            If tei:ab is of type marginal_note, its place must be either 'left_margin' or
            'right_margin'.
          </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ab[@type='dorsal']">
          <sch:assert test=".[@place[contains(., 'verso')]]" xml:lang="en">
            If tei:ab is of type dorsal, its place must be on the verso page.
          </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="n" mode="delete"/>
    <attDef ident="place" mode="replace" usage="req">
      <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-02-04">der Ort des anonymen Textblocks</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2025-02-04">the place of the anonymous block</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-02-04">le lieu du bloc anonyme</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place.ab"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place.add"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rend" mode="replace">
      <datatype>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.rend.add"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.rend.placement"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.rend.rotation"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="type" mode="replace" usage="req">
      <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-01-31">die Art des Textblocks</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2025-01-31">the type of text block</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-01-31">le type de bloc de texte</desc>
      <datatype>
        <dataRef key="ssrq.type.ab"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="xml:id" mode="delete"/>
  </attList>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-fr"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-en"/>
  <remarks xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-02-05">
    <p>Wir verwenden das Element mit den Attributen <att>type</att> und <att>place</att>
        für Vermerke aller Art wie Dorsualnotizen, Kanzleivermerke oder Registraturvermerke,
        sowie für Marginalien.</p>
    <p>Die Vermerke werden in chronologischer Reihenfolge aufgenommen.
        Zeitgleich entstandene Vermerke werden aufgrund der chronologischen Reihenfolge immer an
        der gleichen Stelle aufgeführt. Wenn z. B. bei einem Missiv auf der Rückseite eine
        Dorsualnotiz an erster Stelle steht, dann die Adresse folgt und schliesslich zwei weitere
        Dorsualnotizen, dann steht die Adresse trotzdem an erster Stelle, weil sie der
        chronologisch gesehen erste Eintrag ist.</p>
    <p>Bei Papsturkunden erfolgt die Angabe der Vermerke in folgender Reihenfolge: zuerst die
        Vermerke unter der Plica, dann die auf der Plica und zum Schluss die Vermerke auf der
        Rückseite der Urkunde.</p>
    <p>Alle jeweils zeitgleichen Vermerke werden in Leserichtung
        von oben nach unten und von links nach rechts erfasst. Falls die Leserichtung,
        an der man sich orientieren soll, nicht eindeutig ist, z. B. wenn ein Vermerk auf dem
        Kopf steht, ist ein Kommentar notwendig.
   </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-30">
    <p>We always use the tag together with <att>type</att> and <att>place</att> for notes, dorsal
        notes, chancery notes and registry notes as well as for marginalia.</p>
    <p>In the case of papal documents, the notes are given in the following order: first the notes
        under the plica, then the notes on the plica from left to right, and finally the notes on
        the back of the document from left to right.</p>
    <p>The endorsements and dorsual notes are recorded in chronological order. Contemporaneous
        notes are always listed first because of the chronological order. Contemporaneous notes
        are recorded in reading direction from top to bottom and from left to right. For example,
        if a missive has a dorsal notation on the back in first place, followed by the address and
        finally two more dorsal notations, the address will still be in first place. If the reading
        direction to be followed is not uniform, i.e. a dorsual note is upside down, a comment is
        necessary.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-02-05">
    <p>Nous utilisons l’élément avec les attributs <att>type</att> et <att>place</att> pour toutes
        sortes de notes telles que les notes dorsales, les notes de bureau ou les notes de registre,
        ainsi que pour les notes marginales.</p>
    <p>Les notes sont incluses par ordre chronologique. Les notes créées en même temps sont
        toujours répertoriées au même endroit en raison de l’ordre chronologique. Si p. ex.
        une note dorsale apparaît en premier au dos d’une missive, suivie de l’adresse et enfin
        de deux autres notes dorsales, alors l’adresse est toujours la première, car c’est la
        première entrée chronologiquement.</p>
    <p>Dans le cas des documents papaux, les notes sont données dans l’ordre suivant : d’abord
        les notes sous la plica, puis celles sur la plica et enfin les notes au dos du
        document.</p>
    <p>Toutes les notes simultanées sont enregistrées dans le sens de lecture de haut en bas
          et de gauche à droite. Si le sens de lecture à suivre n’est pas clair, p. ex. si
          une note est à l’envers, un commentaire est nécessaire.</p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
