<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl"
        type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ident="ab" module="linking" mode="change">
  <gloss xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-06-30">Anonymer Textblock</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-30">anonymous block</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-06-30">bloc anonyme</gloss>
  <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-06-30">Enthält eine beliebige Textebene ohne klar definierte Zuordnung.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-30">Contains any text level without a clearly defined assignment.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-06-30">Contient un niveau de texte quelconque sans affectation clairement
        définie.
    </desc>
  <classes mode="replace">
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.global.rendition"/>
    <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.written"/>
    <memberOf key="macro.abContent"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:ref name="ssrq.content.default"/>
    </rng:oneOrMore>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="n" mode="delete"/>
    <attDef ident="place" mode="replace" usage="req">
      <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-05-02">Ort einer Dorsualnotiz, eines Vermerks, eines
                Registraturvermerks oder eines Kanzleivermerks
            </desc>
      <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-05-02">Place of a dorsal note, a note, a registry note or a chancery
                note
            </desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-05-02">Lieu d'une note dorsale, d'une note, d'une note
                d'enregistrement ou d'une note de chancellerie
            </desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place.ab"/>
          <rng:ref name="ssrq.place.add"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rend" mode="replace">
      <datatype>
        <dataRef key="ssrq.rend.add"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="type" mode="replace" usage="req">
      <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-05-02">Klassifikation des Elements</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-05-02">Classification of the element</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-05-02">Classification de l'élément</desc>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="address">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Anschrift</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Adress</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Adresse</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="archiving_reference">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Registraturvermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Registratur’s sign</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Note d’archives</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="chancery_notation">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Kanzleivermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Chancery notation</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Annotation issue d’une chancellerie</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="computatio">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Komputierungsvermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Computatio</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Annotation du computeur</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="dorsal">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Vermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Note</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Note</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="marginal_note">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Marginalie</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Marginal note</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Note</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="sigillant">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Sieglervermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Sigillant’s notes</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Annotation d’un sceau</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="tax">
          <desc xml:lang="de">Taxvermerk</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="en">Tax note</desc>
          <desc xml:lang="fr">Annotation de taxation</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="xml:id" mode="delete"/>
  </attList>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-fr"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ab-en"/>
  <remarks xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-06-30">
    <p>Wir verwenden den Tag immer zusammen mit <att>type</att> und <att>place</att> für Vermerke, Dorsualnotizen,
            Kanzleivermerke und Registraturvermerke sowie für Marginalien.
        </p>
    <p>Bei Papsturkunden erfolgt die Angabe der Vermerke in folgender Reihenfolge: Zuerst die Vermerke unter der
            Plica, dann die Vermerke auf der Plica von links nach rechts und zum Schluss die Vermerke auf der Rückseite
            der Urkunde von links nach rechts.
        </p>
    <p>Die Vermerke und Dorsualnotizen werden in chronologischer Reihenfolge aufgenommen. Zeitgleich entstandene
            Vermerke werden aufgrund der chronologischen Reihenfolge immer an erster Stelle aufgeführt. Zeitgleiche
            Vermerke werden in Leserichtung von oben nach unten und von links nach rechts erfasst. Wenn z. B. bei einem
            Missiv auf der Rückseite ein Dorsualvermerk an erster Stelle steht, dann die Adresse folgt und schliesslich
            zwei weitere Dorsualvermerke, dann steht die Adresse trotzdem an erster Stelle. Falls die Leserichtung, an
            der man sich orientieren soll, nicht einheitlich ist, also ein Dorsualvermerk auf den Kopf steht, ist ein
            Kommentar notwendig.
        </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-30">
    <p>We always use the tag together with <att>type</att> and <att>place</att> for notes, dorsal notes, chancery
            notes and registry notes as well as for marginalia.
        </p>
    <p>In the case of papal documents, the notes are given in the following order: first the notes under the plica,
            then the notes on the plica from left to right, and finally the notes on the back of the document from left
            to right.
        </p>
    <p>The endorsements and dorsual notes are recorded in chronological order. Contemporaneous notes are always
            listed first because of the chronological order. Contemporaneous notes are recorded in reading direction
            from top to bottom and from left to right. For example, if a missive has a dorsal notation on the back
            in first place, followed by the address and finally two more dorsal notations, the address will still be in
            first place. If the reading direction to be followed is not uniform, i.e. a dorsual note is upside down, a
            comment is necessary.
        </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-06-30">
    <p>Nous utilisons toujours cette balise avec <att>type</att> et <att>place</att> pour les mentions, les notes
            dorsales, les mentions de chancellerie et les mentions de registre ainsi que pour les marginalia.
        </p>
    <p>Pour les documents pontificaux, les mentions sont indiquées dans l'ordre suivant : d'abord les mentions sous
            le plica, ensuite les mentions sur le plica de gauche à droite et enfin les mentions au verso du document
            de gauche à droite.
        </p>
    <p>Les annotations et les notes dorsales sont enregistrées dans l'ordre chronologique. En raison de l'ordre
            chronologique, les mentions contemporaines sont toujours mentionnées en premier lieu. Les notes simultanées
            sont enregistrées dans le sens de lecture de haut en bas et de gauche à droite. Si, par exemple, une mention
            dorsale figure au verso d'un missile, suivie de l'adresse et de deux autres mentions dorsales, l'adresse
            figure tout de même en premier lieu. Si le sens de lecture auquel on doit se référer n'est pas uniforme,
            c'est-à-dire si une mention dorsale est à l'envers, un commentaire est nécessaire.
        </p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
