<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl"
        type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ident="ref" module="core" mode="change">
  <gloss xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-02-04">Verweis</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="en" versionDate="2025-02-04">reference</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-02-04">référence</gloss>
  <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-04-28">Enthält einen Verweis.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-04-28">Contains a reference.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-04-28">Contient une référence.</desc>
  <classes mode="replace">
    <memberOf key="att.pointing"/>
    <memberOf key="model.annotationPart.body"/>
    <memberOf key="model.ptrLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <alternate maxOccurs="unbounded">
      <elementRef key="hi"/>
      <textNode/>
    </alternate>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec xml:lang="en" scheme="schematron" ident="refAtts" mode="delete"/>
  <constraintSpec xml:lang="en" scheme="schematron" ident="sch-el-ref" mode="add">
    <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-22">constraint for tei:ref</desc>
    <constraint>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ref[not(*)]">
          <sch:assert test="if (not(.[@target])) then string-length(normalize-space(.)) &gt; 0 else .[@target]">
              tei:ref should contain some text or must use the attribute @target.
          </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec xml:lang="en" scheme="schematron" ident="sch-ref-in-bibl" mode="add">
    <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2024-11-04">constraint for tei:ref in tei:bibl</desc>
    <constraint>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ref[not(ancestor::tei:editorialDecl)][not(parent::tei:note[@type='text_comparison'])]">
          <sch:assert test="./parent::tei:bibl">
              If tei:ref is not part of tei:editorialDecl or tei:note with @type="text_comparison",
              it should be enclosed in tei:bibl.
          </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-en"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-fr"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-en"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-fr"/>
  <remarks xml:lang="de" versionDate="2025-02-06">
    <p>Der Verweis kann auf ein anderes Dokument, die Einleitung, das Register eines
      retrodigitalisierten Bandes, einen Eintrag im HLS, zitierte Literatur etc. zeigen.</p>
    <p>Es ist sinnvoll, Links auf weitere, nicht edierte, aber in einem Archivinformationssystem
      einzeln verzeichnete Quellenstücke innerhalb von <gi>ref</gi> zu setzen. Nicht sinnvoll ist
      es, wenn bei einer einzelnen Urkunde auf den ganzen Urkundenbestand verlinkt wird, weil die
      Einzelurkunde nicht verzeichnet ist. Bei Einträgen aus einem Buch, die man nicht einzeln in
      einem Archivinformationssystem verzeichnen will (wenn das überhaupt möglich ist), kann auf
      das (ganze) Buch, das im Archivkatalog verzeichnet ist, verlinkt werden.</p>
    <p>Wird auf andere Editionen verlinkt, wird zuerst die Signatur der Quelle angegeben, wenn
      die Archivalie konsultiert wurde (Autopsie) oder wenn sich die Signatur via Query
      verifizieren und verlinken lässt. Hat man eine Archivalie anhand einer Edition beurteilt,
      ist nur die Edition anzugeben.</p>
    <p>Wenn man auf eine Quelle, die in einer Editionseinheit der SSRQ ediert wird, verweisen
      möchte, ist es nicht notwendig, die Archivsignatur zu wiederholen, sondern es reicht, auf
      die Stücknummer der Editionseinheit zu verlinken. Ebenso ist es möglich, innerhalb der
      eigenen Editionseinheit von einem Stück auf ein anderes zu referenzieren. Wir verwenden
      dafür die <gi>idno</gi>. Verweise auf andere Stücke werden in <gi>bibl</gi>
      eingeschlossen.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="en" versionDate="2024-11-04">
    <p>The reference can point to another document, the introduction, the index of a retrodigitized
        volume, an entry in the HLS, cited literature, etc. It makes sense to place links within
        <gi>ref</gi> to other source pieces that are not edited but are individually listed in an
        archive information system. It does not make sense if a single certificate is linked to the
        entire stock of certificates because the individual certificate is not listed. In the case
        of entries from a book that one does not want to list individually in an archive
        information system (if that is at all possible), a link can be made to the (entire) book
        that is listed in the archive catalogue. If links are made to other editions, the call
        number of the source is given first if the archival material was consulted (autopsy) or if
        the call number can be verified and linked via query. If an archival item has been assessed
        based on an edition, only the edition needs to be specified. If you want to refer to a
        source that is edited in an edition unit of the SLS, it is not necessary to repeat the
        archival reference, but it is sufficient to link to the item number of the edition unit
        (see example below). It is also possible to reference from one piece to another within your
        own edition unit. We use the <gi>idno</gi> for this.</p>
    <p>References to other pieces are included in <gi>bibl</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2025-02-06">
    <p>Le renvoi peut pointer vers un autre document, l’introduction, le registre d’un volume
      rétro-numérisé, une entrée du DHS, une littérature citée, etc.</p>
    <p>Les référence à des sources non éditées, mais répertoriées dans un système d’information
      archivistique, devraient être signalées par un lien à l’intérieur de <gi>ref</gi>.
      Il n’est toutefois pas judicieux de créer un lien vers l’ensemble du fonds documentaire pour
      un acte isolé. Pour les parties d’un livre (chapitre, contribution) que l’on ne souhaite pas
      répertorier individuellement dans un système d’information archivistique, il est possible
      de créer un lien vers le livre (entier) répertorié dans le catalogue des archives.</p>
    <p>Si l’on établit un lien vers d’autres documents, on indique la cote de la source si le
      document d’archives a été consulté directement ou si la cote peut être vérifiée et reliée
      via un système d’information archivistique. En revanche, si l’on a pris connaissance d’une
      archive sur la seule base d’une édition, seule l’édition doit être indiquée.</p>
    <p>Si l’on souhaite faire référence à une source éditée dans une unité d’édition des SDS,
      il n’est pas nécessaire de répéter la cote de l’archive, mais il suffit de faire un lien
      vers le numéro de la pièce au sein de l’unité d’édition en question. De même, il est
      possible de référencer une pièce qui se situe à l’intérieur de sa propre unité d’édition.
      Nous utilisons pour cela le <gi>idno</gi> de la pièce. Les renvois aux autres pièces sont
      signalés dans <gi>bibl</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
