<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl"
        type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ident="ref" module="core" mode="change">
  <desc xml:lang="de" versionDate="2023-04-28">Enthält einen Verweis.</desc>
  <classes mode="replace">
    <memberOf key="att.pointing"/>
    <memberOf key="model.annotationPart.body"/>
    <memberOf key="model.ptrLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <alternate maxOccurs="unbounded">
      <elementRef key="hi"/>
      <textNode/>
    </alternate>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="refAtts" mode="delete"/>
  <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="sch-el-ref" mode="add">
    <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2023-06-22">Specific schematron rule for tei:ref</desc>
    <constraint>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ref[not(*)]">
          <sch:assert test="if (not(.[@target])) then string-length(normalize-space(.)) &gt; 0 else .[@target]"><sch:name/>
                        should contain some text or must use the attribute @target.
                    </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="sch-ref-in-bibl" mode="add">
    <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2024-11-04">Specific schematron rule for tei:ref</desc>
    <constraint>
      <sch:pattern>
        <sch:rule context="tei:ref[not(ancestor::tei:editorialDecl)][not(parent::tei:note[@type='text_comparison'])]">
          <sch:assert test="./parent::tei:bibl">If <sch:name/> is not part of tei:editorialDecl
              or tei:note with @type="text_comparison", it should be enclosed in tei:bibl.
          </sch:assert>
        </sch:rule>
      </sch:pattern>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-en"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-print-fr"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-de"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-en"/>
  <xi:include href="examples.xml" xpointer="ex-ref-urn-fr"/>
  <remarks xml:lang="de" versionDate="2024-11-04">
    <p>Der Verweis kann auf ein anderes Dokument, die Einleitung, das Register eines retrodigitalisierten Bandes,
            einen Eintrag im HLS, zitierte Literatur etc. zeigen. Es ist sinnvoll, Links auf weitere, nicht edierte,
            aber in einem Archivinformationssystem einzeln verzeichnete Quellenstücke innerhalb von <gi>ref</gi> zu
            setzen. Nicht sinnvoll ist es, wenn bei einer einzelnen Urkunde auf den ganzen Urkundenbestand verlinkt
            wird, weil die Einzelurkunde nicht verzeichnet ist. Bei Einträgen aus einem Buch, die man nicht einzeln in
            einem Archivinformationssystem verzeichnen will (wenn das überhaupt möglich ist), kann auf das (ganze) Buch,
            das im Archivkatalog verzeichnet ist, verlinkt werden. Wird auf andere Editionen verlinkt, wird zuerst die
            Signatur der Quelle angegeben, wenn die Archivalie konsultiert wurde (Autopsie) oder wenn sich die Signatur
            via Query verifizieren und verlinken lässt. Hat man eine Archivalie anhand einer Edition beurteilt, ist nur
            die Edition anzugeben. Wenn man auf eine Quelle, die in einer Editionseinheit der SSRQ ediert wird,
            verweisen möchte, ist es nicht notwendig, die Archivsignatur zu wiederholen, sondern es reicht, auf die
            Stücknummer der Editionseinheit zu verlinken (vgl. Beispiel unten). Ebenso ist es möglich, innerhalb der
            eigenen Editionseinheit von einem Stück auf ein anderes zu referenzieren. Wir verwenden dafür
            die <gi>idno</gi>.
        </p>
    <p>Verweise auf andere Stücke werden in <gi>bibl</gi> eingeschlossen.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="en" versionDate="2024-11-04">
    <p>The reference can point to another document, the introduction, the index of a retrodigitized volume, an entry
            in the HLS, cited literature, etc. It makes sense to place links within <gi>ref</gi> to other source pieces
            that are not edited but are individually listed in an archive information system. It does not make sense if
            a single certificate is linked to the entire stock of certificates because the individual certificate is not
            listed. In the case of entries from a book that one does not want to list individually in an archive
            information system (if that is at all possible), a link can be made to the (entire) book that is listed in
            the archive catalogue. If links are made to other editions, the call number of the source is given first if
            the archival material was consulted (autopsy) or if the call number can be verified and linked via query. If
            an archival item has been assessed based on an edition, only the edition needs to be specified. If you want
            to refer to a source that is edited in an edition unit of the SSRQ, it is not necessary to repeat the
            archival reference, but it is sufficient to link to the item number of the edition unit (see example below).
            It is also possible to reference from one piece to another within your own edition unit. We use
            the <gi>idno</gi> for this.
        </p>
    <p>References to other pieces are included in <gi>bibl</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2023-07-20">
    <p>La référence peut pointer vers un autre document, l'introduction, l'index d'un volume rétronumérisé, une
            entrée dans l'HLS, une littérature citée, etc. Il est logique de placer des liens dans <gi>ref</gi> vers
            d'autres éléments sources qui ne sont pas édités mais qui sont répertoriés individuellement dans un système
            d'information d'archives. Cela n'a pas de sens qu'un seul certificat soit lié à l'ensemble du stock de
            certificats parce que le certificat individuel n'est pas répertorié. Dans le cas d'entrées d'un livre que
            l'on ne souhaite pas répertorier individuellement dans un système d'information d'archives (si cela est
            possible), un lien peut être établi vers le livre (entier) répertorié dans le catalogue d'archives. Si des
            liens sont établis vers d'autres éditions, la cote de la source est indiquée en premier si le matériel
            d'archives a été consulté (autopsie) ou si la cote peut être vérifiée et liée par requête. Si un document
            d'archives a été évalué sur la base d'une édition, seule l'édition doit être spécifiée. Si vous voulez faire
            référence à une source qui est éditée dans une unité d'édition du SSRQ, il n'est pas nécessaire de répéter
            la référence archivistique, mais il suffit de faire le lien avec le numéro d'item de l'unité d'édition (voir
            exemple ci-dessous). Il est également possible de référencer d'une pièce à l'autre au sein de votre propre
            unité d'édition. Nous utilisons le <gi>idno</gi> pour cela.
        </p>
    <p>Les références à d'autres pièces sont incluses dans <gi>bibl</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
